and we are embedded in a very large cosmos,
وكذلك نحن جزء لا يتجزأ من هذا الكون الواسع،
and the fact is that we are not very good at understanding reality
الحقيقة أننا لسنا جيدون في فهمنا للواقع
at either of those scales,
فى كلتا هاتين الحالتين،
and that's because our brains
وذلك لأن عقولنا
haven't evolved to understand the world at that scale.
لم تتطور بشكل كافٍ لتفهم العالم عند هذا المستوى.
Instead, we're trapped on this very thin slice of perception
إن إدراكنا ينحصر في جزء صغير جداً من الإدراك
right in the middle.
تحديدًا في المنتصف.
But it gets strange, because even at that slice of reality that we call home,
وهذا غريب، لأنه حتى هذا الجزء الصغير من الواقع الذي نطلق عليه "الموطن"،
we're not seeing most of the action that's going on.
لا نرى فيه معظم الأحداث التي تدور حولنا.
So take the colors of our world.
لنأخذ مثلًا، الألوان التي تزين عالمنا
This is light waves, electromagnetic radiation that bounces off objects
إنها موجات ضوئية وإشعاعات كهرومغناطيسية تنعكس على الأجسام
and it hits specialized receptors in the back of our eyes.
ثم تصطدم بمستقبلات معينة في الجزء الخلفي من أعيننا،
But we're not seeing all the waves out there.
لكننا لا نرى كل الموجات الموجودة من حولنا.
In fact, what we see
في الحقيقة، ما نراه
is less than a 10 trillionth of what's out there.
هو جزء واحد فقط من 10 تريليونات مما هو موجود.
So you have radio waves and microwaves
مثلًا لديكم، موجات دقيقة وموجات الراديو
and X-rays and gamma rays passing through your body right now
والأشعة السينية وأشعة غاما تعبر أجسامكم الآن،
and you're completely unaware of it,
وأنتم قطعًا لا تدركون وجودها،
because you don't come with the proper biological receptors
لأنكم لستم مجهزين بالمستقبلات الحيوية المناسبة
for picking it up.
حتى تستطيعوا التقاطها.
There are thousands of cell phone conversations
ثمة آلاف من المحادثات الهاتفية
passing through you right now,
تعبر من خلالكم في هذه اللحظة،
and you're utterly blind to it.
وأنتم مغيبين عنها تمامًا.
Now, it's not that these things are inherently unseeable.
لكن، هذا لا يعني أن هذه الأشياء غير مرئية بطبيعتها.
Snakes include some infrared in their reality,
فالثعابين مثلًا، تستشعر الأشعة تحت الحمراء
and honeybees include ultraviolet in their view of the world,
والنحل له قدرة على رؤية الأشعة فوق البنفسجية.
and of course we build machines in the dashboards of our cars
وها هي لوحات القيادة في سياراتنا مزودة بآلات
to pick up on signals in the radio frequency range,
تلتقط بها الإشارات في نطاق التردد اللاسلكي.
and we built machines in hospitals to pick up on the X-ray range.
وزودنا المستشفيات بآلات لالتقاط صور بأشعة إكس،
But you can't sense any of those by yourself,
لكنك لا تستطيع الشعور بأيًا منها،
at least not yet,
أو على الأقل ليس بعد،
because you don't come equipped with the proper sensors.
لأنك غير مجهّز بأجهزة الاستشعار المناسبة.
Now, what this means is that our experience of reality
ما يعنيه هذا، أن تجربتنا عن الواقع
is constrained by our biology,
محدودة بطبيعتنا البشرية،
and that goes against the common sense notion
وذلك يدحض المفهوم الشائع للحواس
that our eyes and our ears and our fingertips
بأن أعيننا وآذاننا وأناملنا
are just picking up the objective reality that's out there.
تشعر بكل ما هو محسوس من حولنا.
Instead, our brains are sampling just a little bit of the world.
لكن الحقيقة أن عقولنا تدرك القليل فقط مما هو موجود.
Now, across the animal kingdom,
ففي مملكة الحيوانات،
different animals pick up on different parts of reality.
كل حيوان له القدرة على التقاط جزء مختلف من الواقع الحسي
So in the blind and deaf world of the tick,
مثلًا في عالم القُراد الأعمى و الأصم
the important signals are temperature and butyric acid;
أهم الإشارات هي الحرارة و حمض البيوتريك
in the world of the black ghost knifefish,
أما عالم "السمكة الفراشة "
its sensory world is lavishly colored by electrical fields;
فهو ملوّن تماما بالمجال الكهربائي
and for the echolocating bat,
أما بالنسبة للخفاش الذي يعتمد على الصدى
its reality is constructed out of air compression waves.
فواقعه يتكون من انضغاط موجات الهواء
That's the slice of their ecosystem that they can pick up on,
هذه هي حدود نظامها البيئي التي تستطيع التقاطه،
and we have a word for this in science.
وثمة مصطلح لهذا المجال العلمي
It's called the umwelt,
يدعى " البيئة الحسية"
which is the German word for the surrounding world.
وهي كلمة ألمانية تعني العالم المحيط بنا.
Now, presumably, every animal assumes
من المحتمل أن كل حيوان يفترض
that its umwelt is the entire objective reality out there,
أن البيئة الحسية هو الواقع الكلي الموجود هناك،
because why would you ever stop to imagine
فلماذا لا نذهب بخيالنا
that there's something beyond what we can sense.
أن هنالك شيء ما وراء حدود حواسنا
Instead, what we all do is we accept reality
ولكن بدلا عن ذلك نتقبل الواقع
as it's presented to us.
كما يُقدّم لنا.
Let's do a consciousness-raiser on this.
دعنا ننعش أدمغتنا
Imagine that you are a bloodhound dog.
ولتتخيل أنك كلب صيدٍ،
Your whole world is about smelling.
إذاً، سيتمحورعالمك كله حول حاسة الشم.
You've got a long snout that has 200 million scent receptors in it,
فلديك أنف طويل به 200 مليون خلية من مستقبلات الروائح،
and you have wet nostrils that attract and trap scent molecules,
ولديك فتحتي أنف رطبتين يقومان بجذب جزيئات الروائح
and your nostrils even have slits so you can take big nosefuls of air.
ويوجد بها شقوق تمكن من التقاط أكبر كم من الانبعاثات في الهواء
Everything is about smell for you.
كل شيء بالنسبة لك هو عن الشم،
So one day, you stop in your tracks with a revelation.
ويوماً ما تدرك الحقيقة،
You look at your human owner and you think,
تنظر لصاحبك البشري وتطرق مفكراً
"What is it like to have the pitiful, impoverished nose of a human?
"كيف كنت لأبدو لو أن أنفي صغير مسلوب القدرة يرثى له كأنوف البشر؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
What is it like when you take a feeble little noseful of air?
كيف يبدو حالك عندما يمتلئ أنفك باستنشاقك كمية لا تذكر من الهواء؟
How can you not know that there's a cat 100 yards away,
كيف لا تدرك أنه توجد قطة على بعد 100 ياردة
or that your neighbor was on this very spot six hours ago?"
أو أن جارك كان في هذا المكان منذ ست ساعات بالضبط؟"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So because we're humans,
ولأننا بشر،
we've never experienced that world of smell,
لم نجرب قط عالم الرائحة ذلك
so we don't miss it,
لذلك لا نكترث به
because we are firmly settled into our umwelt.
لأننا مرتبطون وبقوة بما هو حولنا.
But the question is, do we have to be stuck there?
والسؤال الذي يطرح نفسه : هل نبقى مكتوفي الأيدي ؟
So as a neuroscientist, I'm interested in the way that technology
وبصفتي متخصص في علم الأعصاب، فأنا مولع بمسار التكنولوجيا وتطورها
might expand our umwelt,
ربما توسع آفاق معرفتنا بالبيئة المحيطة،
and how that's going to change the experience of being human.
وكيف ستغير التكنولوجيا تجربة الإنسان:
So we already know that we can marry our technology to our biology,
ذلك بأنه بات معلوماً من الممكن المزاوجة بين التكنولوجيا وعلم الأحياء،
because there are hundreds of thousands of people walking around
لأن هنالك مئات الآلاف من البشر يتجولون حولنا
with artificial hearing and artificial vision.
بسمع صناعي ونظر صناعي
So the way this works is, you take a microphone and you digitize the signal,
الطريقة التي يعمل بها الجهاز أنّ مايكروفون يحوِّل الموجات إلى إشارات رقمية
and you put an electrode strip directly into the inner ear.
ويُوضع شريطاً كهربائياً في الأذن الداخلية
Or, with the retinal implant, you take a camera
أو عملية زرع شبكية العين، حيث تستعين بكاميرا
and you digitize the signal, and then you plug an electrode grid
وتحول الإشارة إلى إشارة رقمية ثم تُلصق بشبكة كهربائية
directly into the optic nerve.
مباشرة على العصب البصري.
And as recently as 15 years ago,
منذ 15 عاماً
there were a lot of scientists who thought these technologies wouldn't work.
شكك الكثير من العلماء في نجاح تلك التقنيات
Why? It's because these technologies speak the language of Silicon Valley,
لماذا؟ لأن هذه التقنيات ذات طابع متفرد إنها تتحدث بلغة وادي السيليكون
and it's not exactly the same dialect as our natural biological sense organs.
وهي ليست نفس لهجة أعضاء الحس الحيوية لدينا
But the fact is that it works;
ولكن الواقع أثبت أنها نجحت،
the brain figures out how to use the signals just fine.
فالعقل يجيد استخدام هذه الإشارات
Now, how do we understand that?
والسؤال الآن، كيف نفهم ذلك؟
Well, here's the big secret:
إليكم السر الخطير:
Your brain is not hearing or seeing any of this.
عقلك لا يسمع ولا يرى أيًا من تلك الإشارات
Your brain is locked in a vault of silence and darkness inside your skull.
إن العقل متقوقع في محيط صامت ومظلم داخل الجمجمة
All it ever sees are electrochemical signals
العقل لا يرى سوى الإشارات الكهروكيميائية
that come in along different data cables,
والتي تأتيه عبر وصلات مختلفة
and this is all it has to work with, and nothing more.
وهذا كل ما في الأمر، ليس أكثر من ذلك
Now, amazingly,
والمدهش
the brain is really good at taking in these signals
أن العقل بارع وبشدة في التقاط هذه الإشارات
and extracting patterns and assigning meaning,
واستخلاص الأنماط وتعريفها
so that it takes this inner cosmos and puts together a story
بحيث يكوّن عوالم داخلية ويجمعها سوية في قصة
of this, your subjective world.
وبذلك ينشأ عالمك الخاص.
But here's the key point:
لكن الفكرة الرئيسية
Your brain doesn't know, and it doesn't care,
أن عقلك لا يعلم ولا يكترث
where it gets the data from.
بمصدر الحصول على المعلومات
Whatever information comes in, it just figures out what to do with it.
فمهما كانت المعلومات الوافدة، يقوم العقل باكتشاف كيفية توظيفها
And this is a very efficient kind of machine.
وهذا أشبه ما يكون بآلة على درجة عالية من الكفاءة
It's essentially a general purpose computing device,
كجهاز حاسوب متعدد الأغراض
and it just takes in everything
يتفحّص كل شيء
and figures out what it's going to do with it,
ثم يكتشف كيفية توظيفها
and that, I think, frees up Mother Nature
وذلك من شأنه تحرير "الطبيعة الأم"
to tinker around with different sorts of input channels.
من العبث بالأنواع المختلفة من قنوات الإدخال
So I call this the P.H. model of evolution,
أطلق على ذلك نموذج التطور P.H
and I don't want to get too technical here,
لا أريد أن أخوض في مصطلحات تقنية معقّدة
but P.H. stands for Potato Head,
لكن P.H هو اختصار لمصطلح "رأس البطاطا"
and I use this name to emphasize that all these sensors
وأستخدم هذه التسمية للتأكيد على أن جميع أجهزة الاستشعار هذه
that we know and love, like our eyes and our ears and our fingertips,
التي نعرفها ونحبها كأعيننا وآذاننا وأطراف أصابعنا
these are merely peripheral plug-and-play devices:
تعمل تماماً كالأجهزة الملحقة بالحاسوب:
You stick them in, and you're good to go.
نستطيع استخدامها حالما تقوم بتركيبها.
The brain figures out what to do with the data that comes in.
يعمل الدماغ على توظيف المعلومات التي يتلقاها.
And when you look across the animal kingdom,
عندما نلقي نظرة على مملكة الحيوانات
you find lots of peripheral devices.
تجد الكثير من الأجهزة الملحقة
So snakes have heat pits with which to detect infrared,
تمتلك الأفاعي مثلاً تجاويف تتحسس الحرارة
and the ghost knifefish has electroreceptors,
أما السمكة الفراشة فتمتلك مستقبلات كهربائية
and the star-nosed mole has this appendage
ويمتلك الخلد ذو الأنف النجمي ذيلاً ملحقاً
with 22 fingers on it
يتألف من 22 إصبعاً
with which it feels around and constructs a 3D model of the world,
يشعر من خلاله بما يحيط به ويبني بواسطته عالماً ثلاثي الأبعاد
and many birds have magnetite so they can orient
وتمتلك الكثير من الطيور مغناطيساً يمكنها من التوجيه
to the magnetic field of the planet.
عبر الحقل المغناطيسي للكرة الأرضية.
So what this means is that nature doesn't have to continually
ما يعنيه هذا أن الطبيعة ليس عليها دائما
redesign the brain.
إعادة تصميم الدماغ
Instead, with the principles of brain operation established,
وإنما من خلال إنشاء مبادئ لعمل الدماغ
all nature has to worry about is designing new peripherals.
يجب أن يتمحور دور الطبيعة على تصميم أجهزة ملحقة جديدة
Okay. So what this means is this:
بمعنى آخر
The lesson that surfaces
العبرة التي تطفو على السطح
is that there's nothing really special or fundamental
أن ليس ثمة ما هو خاص أو أساسي
about the biology that we come to the table with.
حيال علم الأحياء الذي أتينا به
It's just what we have inherited
هو فقط الإرث الذي جنيناه
from a complex road of evolution.
عبر مسيرة معقدة من التطور.
But it's not what we have to stick with,
لكن لا ينبغي التعلق به،
and our best proof of principle of this
وأفضل دليل على هذا المبدأ
comes from what's called sensory substitution.
يأتي مما نطلق عليه "البديل الحسي".
And that refers to feeding information into the brain
وهذا يشير للمعلومات الوافدة إلى الدماغ
via unusual sensory channels,
عبر قنوات حسية خاصة،
and the brain just figures out what to do with it.
والدماغ يتدبر أمر التصرف بها.
Now, that might sound speculative,
قد يبدو ذلك تأملياً
but the first paper demonstrating this was published in the journal Nature in 1969.
لكن الورقة الأولى التي شرحت هذا وقع نشرها في صحيفة "ناتشر" في عام 1969.
So a scientist named Paul Bach-y-Rita
قام عالم يدعى (بول باخ واي ريتا)
put blind people in a modified dental chair,
بوضع أناس كفيفين على كرسي أسنان معدّل،
and he set up a video feed,
وقام بتركيب كاميرا تسجيل،
and he put something in front of the camera,
ووضع شيئاً أمام الكاميرا،
and then you would feel that
حينها ستشعر أنه
poked into your back with a grid of solenoids.
ثمة شيء مغروس في ظهرك بشبكة من الملفات اللولبية.
So if you wiggle a coffee cup in front of the camera,
فإذا كان هناك فنجان قهوة أمام الكاميرا،
you're feeling that in your back,
فستشعر بذلك في ظهرك،
and amazingly, blind people got pretty good
وقد تجاوب المكفوفون بشكل مذهل
at being able to determine what was in front of the camera
في تحديد الجسم القابع أمام الكاميرا
just by feeling it in the small of their back.
وكل ذلك من خلال الشعور به في منطقة الظهر.
Now, there have been many modern incarnations of this.
ثمة الكثير من الدراسات الحديثة التي تجسد هذا الطرح.
The sonic glasses take a video feed right in front of you
تعرض النظارات الصوتية الفيديو أمامك
and turn that into a sonic landscape,
ثم تحوله إلى مشهد صوتي،
so as things move around, and get closer and farther,
وعندما تتحرك الأشياء وتقترب وتبتعد،
it sounds like "Bzz, bzz, bzz."
يصدر عن النظارات صوت مميز.
It sounds like a cacophony,
أشبه بنغمات متنافرة،
but after several weeks, blind people start getting pretty good
لكن بعد عدة أسابيع يبلي الكفيف حسناً
at understanding what's in front of them
بإدراك ما هو أمامه
just based on what they're hearing.
بناء على ما يسمعه.
And it doesn't have to be through the ears:
وليس بالضرورة عن طريق الآذان:
this system uses an electrotactile grid on the forehead,
فالنظام يستخدم شبكة حسية كهربائية يتم تثبيتها على الجبهة،
so whatever's in front of the video feed, you're feeling it on your forehead.
وكل ما يقبع أمام الكاميرا تشعر به في جبهتك.
Why the forehead? Because you're not using it for much else.
لماذا الجبهة؟ لأنك لا تستعملها لأي غرض آخر.
The most modern incarnation is called the brainport,
أحدث الاختراعات اليوم يدعى "منفذ الدماغ"،
and this is a little electrogrid that sits on your tongue,
وهو عبارة عن شبكة كهربائية صغيرة يتم تثبيتها على اللسان،
and the video feed gets turned into these little electrotactile signals,
تقوم بتحويل الصورة إلى إشارات حسية كهربائية صغيرة،
and blind people get so good at using this that they can throw a ball into a basket,
ويجيد الكفيف استخدام هذه التقنية لدرجة أن بإمكانهم إدخال الكرة في السلة،
or they can navigate complex obstacle courses.
كما يمكنهم الملاحة في مسارات معقدة.
They can come to see through their tongue.
يستطيع الرؤية من خلال لسانه.
Now, that sounds completely insane, right?
يبدو الأمر ضرباً من الجنون، أليس كذلك؟
But remember, all vision ever is
لكن تذكروا، الرؤية ما هي إلا..
is electrochemical signals coursing around in your brain.
إشارات كهروكيماوية تتجول في أنحاء دماغك.
Your brain doesn't know where the signals come from.
يجهل دماغك مصدر هذه الإشارات.
It just figures out what to do with them.
كل ما يفعله أنه يقوم بتوظيفها.
So my interest in my lab is sensory substitution for the deaf,
يتركز اهتمامي في تجاربي على البديل الحسي للصم،
and this is a project I've undertaken
وقد تبنّيت هذا المشروع
with a graduate student in my lab, Scott Novich,
مع أحد الطلاب المتخرجين في مختبري (سكوت نوفيتش)،
who is spearheading this for his thesis.
والذي يتخذه موضوعاً لأطروحته.
And here is what we wanted to do:
إليكم ما أردنا فعله:
we wanted to make it so that sound from the world gets converted
أردنا أن نبتكر جهازاً لتحويل الصوت الصادر
in some way so that a deaf person can understand what is being said.
بحيث يستطيع الأصم فهم ما يُقال.
And we wanted to do this, given the power and ubiquity of portable computing,
وأردنا القيام بذلك بالاستعانة بالأدوات الحاسوبية المحمولة،
we wanted to make sure that this would run on cell phones and tablets,
أردنا التأكد من أن هذا الجهاز يعمل على الهواتف النقالة والأجهزة اللوحية،
and also we wanted to make this a wearable,
وكنا ننوي أن نجعل هذا الجهاز قابلاً للارتداء،
something that you could wear under your clothing.
جهاز يمكن ارتداؤه تحت الملابس.
So here's the concept.
هذه هي الفكرة.
So as I'm speaking, my sound is getting captured by the tablet,
عندما أتحدث، يلتقط الجهاز اللوحي صوتي،
and then it's getting mapped onto a vest that's covered in vibratory motors,
ثم يتحول إلى رسم على سترة مزوّدة برجّاجات،
just like the motors in your cell phone.
تماماً كالموجود في هاتفك النقال
So as I'm speaking,
عندما أتحدث،
the sound is getting translated to a pattern of vibration on the vest.
يتم ترجمة الصوت إلى ذبذبات على السترة.
Now, this is not just conceptual:
لم يعد هذا محض خيال:
this tablet is transmitting Bluetooth, and I'm wearing the vest right now.
هذا الجهاز اللوحي يرسل بالبلوتوث وها أنا أرتدي السترة الآن.
So as I'm speaking -- (Applause) --
عندما أتحدث -- (تصفيق) --
the sound is getting translated into dynamic patterns of vibration.
يتم ترجمة الصوت إلى نمط ديناميكي من الاهتزاز
I'm feeling the sonic world around me.
إنني أشعر بالعالم الصوتي من حولي.
So, we've been testing this with deaf people now,
نقوم باختبار هذا الاختراع على الصم الآن،
and it turns out that after just a little bit of time,
وتبين أنه بعد فترة ليست بطويلة،
people can start feeling, they can start understanding
سيبدأ الناس بالشعور بها وباستيعاب
the language of the vest.
لغة السترة.
So this is Jonathan. He's 37 years old. He has a master's degree.
ها هو (جوناثان)، عمره 27 عاماً. حاصل على شهادة ماجستير
He was born profoundly deaf,
لقد ولد أصماً
which means that there's a part of his umwelt that's unavailable to him.
ما يعني أن جزءً من وسيلة الإدراك غير متوفر بالنسبة له
So we had Jonathan train with the vest for four days, two hours a day,
خضع (جوناثان) للتدريب على السترة لأربعة أيام، ساعتان يومياً
and here he is on the fifth day.
وها هو يتدرب لليوم الخامس.
Scott Novich: You.
سكوت نوفيتش: أنت.
David Eagleman: So Scott says a word, Jonathan feels it on the vest,
دافيد إنغليمان: يقول (سكوت) كلمة ويشعر (جوناثان) بها من خلال السترة
and he writes it on the board.
ثم يكتبها على اللّوح
SN: Where. Where.
سكوت نوفيتش: أين.
DE: Jonathan is able to translate this complicated pattern of vibrations
يستطيع (جوناثان) ترجمة هذا النمط المعقد من الاهتزازات
into an understanding of what's being said.
إلى إدراك ما يُقال.
SN: Touch. Touch.
سكوت نوفيتش: لمس.
DE: Now, he's not doing this --
لا يقوم بذلك--
(Applause) --
(تصفيق)--
Jonathan is not doing this consciously, because the patterns are too complicated,
لا يقوم (جوناثان) بذلك بعقله الواعي لأن الأنماط معقدة جداً،
but his brain is starting to unlock the pattern that allows it to figure out
لكن دماغه بدأ بفك شيفرة الأنماط مما أتاح له فهم
what the data mean,
معنى البيانات،
and our expectation is that, after wearing this for about three months,
ونتوقع أنه بعد ثلاثة أشهر من ارتداء هذه السترة،
he will have a direct perceptual experience of hearing
سيتمكن من فهم كل ما يُقال
in the same way that when a blind person passes a finger over braille,
بنفس الطريقة التي يمرر بها الكفيف أصبعه على طريقة بريل،
the meaning comes directly off the page without any conscious intervention at all.
حيث يتم استيعاب المعنى مباشرة دون تدخل العقل الواعي.
Now, this technology has the potential to be a game-changer,
لهذه التقنية القدرة على إحداث تغيير في قواعد اللعبة،
because the only other solution for deafness is a cochlear implant,
فالبديل الوحيد للصم هو زرع قوقعة،
and that requires an invasive surgery.
وهذا يتطلب تدخلاً جراحيا.
And this can be built for 40 times cheaper than a cochlear implant,
أما هذا الاختراع فهو أرخص من زرع القوقعة بأربعين مرة،
which opens up this technology globally, even for the poorest countries.
مما يفتح الباب أمام هذه التقنية عالمياً حتى في البلدان الأكثر فقراً.
Now, we've been very encouraged by our results with sensory substitution,
إن النتائج المنبثقة عن البديل الحسي مشجعة جداً،
but what we've been thinking a lot about is sensory addition.
لكن ما يشغل تفكيرنا كثيراً هو إضافة حاسة جديدة
How could we use a technology like this to add a completely new kind of sense,
كيف نوظف تقنية كهذه في إضافة حاسة جديدة
to expand the human umvelt?
لتوسيع حيز الإدراك البشري؟
For example, could we feed real-time data from the Internet
مثلاً، هل نستطيع تزويد العقل البشري
directly into somebody's brain,
ببيانات مباشرة من الإنترنت
and can they develop a direct perceptual experience?
وهل نستطيع بذلك تطوير الأجهزة الملحقة؟
So here's an experiment we're doing in the lab.
إليكم تجربة نقوم بها في المختبر
A subject is feeling a real-time streaming feed from the Net of data
شخص يشعر بالبيانات المزودة مباشرة من الإنترنت
for five seconds.
لمدة 5 ثوانٍ
Then, two buttons appear, and he has to make a choice.
ثم يظهر اثنين من الأزرار ويجب على الشخص الاختيار
He doesn't know what's going on.
إنه لا يعلم ما الذي يحدث
He makes a choice, and he gets feedback after one second.
يقوم بالاختيار ثم يتلقى إفادة في ثانية واحدة
Now, here's the thing:
الآن، هذا هو المثير
The subject has no idea what all the patterns mean,
الشخص ليست لديه فكرة عما تعنيه أي من تلك الأنماط،
but we're seeing if he gets better at figuring out which button to press.
لكننا سنرى إن كان سيكتشف أي زر هو الصحيح،
He doesn't know that what we're feeding
هو لا يعرف أن ما نغذيه من بيانات
is real-time data from the stock market,
هي بيانات فورية من سوق الأسهم،
and he's making buy and sell decisions.
لكنه يتخذ قرارات بيع وشراء.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And the feedback is telling him whether he did the right thing or not.
ثم يحصل على رد يخبره هل كان قراره صحيحا أم لا.
And what we're seeing is, can we expand the human umvelt
وما نراه أننا يمكننا توسيع مدارك الإنسان
so that he comes to have, after several weeks,
وبالتالي يصبح بعد عدة أسابيع
a direct perceptual experience of the economic movements of the planet.
خبير مُدرك للحركة الاقتصادية في العالم.
So we'll report on that later to see how well this goes.
سنتحدث عن ذلك لاحقا، لنريكم كيف يجري الأمر
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Here's another thing we're doing:
وهذا شيء آخر سنفعله:
During the talks this morning, we've been automatically scraping Twitter
أثناء محادثات TED منذ الصباح، ونحن نقوم بالبحث آليًا في تويتر
for the TED2015 hashtag,
عن هاشتاغ TED2015 #
and we've been doing an automated sentiment analysis,
وأيضا نقوم بالتحليل الآلي للآراء،
which means, are people using positive words or negative words or neutral?
ما يعني، هل يستخدم الناس كلمات إيجابية أم سلبية أم آراءهم محايدة،
And while this has been going on,
وفي هذه الأثناء،
I have been feeling this,
وأنا أشعر بهذا،
and so I am plugged in to the aggregate emotion
وبالتالي أنا موصول بأحاسيس تشمل
of thousands of people in real time,
آلاف البشر فوريًا وفي الزمن الفعلي
and that's a new kind of human experience, because now I can know
وهذه تجربة جديدة للإنسان، لأنني أعلم الآن
how everyone's doing and how much you're loving this.
كيف يشعر الجميع، ولأي مدى أنتم مستمتعون بهذه المحادثة.
(Laughter) (Applause)
(ضحك) (تصفيق)
It's a bigger experience than a human can normally have.
إنها تجربة أكبر مما اعتاد عليه الإنسان.
We're also expanding the umvelt of pilots.
قمنا أيضا باستخدام التجربة مع الطيارين
So in this case, the vest is streaming nine different measures
في هذه الحالة، السترة تقوم بحساب 9 مقاييس مختلفة
from this quadcopter,
ابتداءً من الطوافة،
so pitch and yaw and roll and orientation and heading,
والميل والتعرجات والدوران والتوجيه والعنوان
and that improves this pilot's ability to fly it.
وهذا يطوّر قدرة الطيار على القيادة.
It's essentially like he's extending his skin up there, far away.
فهذا كأنه يمدّد جسده ويذهب به بعيدًا وهو جالس في مكانه.
And that's just the beginning.
وهذه مجرد بداية
What we're envisioning is taking a modern cockpit full of gauges
نحن نتطلع لقمرة قيادة حديثة، مليئة بأجهزة القياس
and instead of trying to read the whole thing, you feel it.
وبدلًا من محاولة قراءة كل شيء، فقط نشعر به.
We live in a world of information now,
نحن اليوم نعيش في عصر المعلومات،
and there is a difference between accessing big data
ويوجد فرق بين الحصول على البيانات
and experiencing it.
وبين تجربة هذه البيانات والشعور بها.
So I think there's really no end to the possibilities
لذلك أعتقد أنه لا نهاية لإمكانيات
on the horizon for human expansion.
على صعيد التوسّع البشري.
Just imagine an astronaut being able to feel
فقط تخيّل رائد فضاء له القدرة على الشعور
the overall health of the International Space Station,
بجملة الحالة الصحية للكوكب من محطة الفضاء الدولية
or, for that matter, having you feel the invisible states of your own health,
أو في ذات السياق، شعورك بحالتك الصحية للأعراض غير المرئية،
like your blood sugar and the state of your microbiome,
كنسبة السكر في دمك أو الميكروبات في جسمك
or having 360-degree vision or seeing in infrared or ultraviolet.
أو القدرة على الرؤية في نطاق 360 درجة أو رؤية الأشعة تحت الحمراء وفوق البنفسجية
So the key is this: As we move into the future,
بيت القصيد أنه، بينما نحن نتقدم في المستقبل
we're going to increasingly be able to choose our own peripheral devices.
ستزداد فرص إمكانية اختيار أجهزة خارجية
We no longer have to wait for Mother Nature's sensory gifts
لن يكون علينا انتظار ما تجود علينا الطبيعة به الأم من حواس
on her timescales,
أو جداولها الزمنية
but instead, like any good parent, she's given us the tools that we need
بدلًا من ذلك، كأي أم جيّدة، ستمنحنا فقط الأدوات التي نحتاج إليها
to go out and define our own trajectory.
لنذهب خارجًا ونحدد مسارنا الخاص.
So the question now is,
لكن السؤال الذي يطرح نفسه:
how do you want to go out and experience your universe?
بأي طريقة تريد اكتشاف عالمك؟
Thank you.
شكرًا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Chris Anderson: Can you feel it? DE: Yeah.
كريس أندرسون: هل تشعر بهذا؟ ديفيد: نعم.
Actually, this was the first time I felt applause on the vest.
في الحقيقة كانت هذه المرة الأولى التي أشعر فيها بالإطراء على السترة
It's nice. It's like a massage. (Laughter)
إنها جميلة، تشبه التدليك. (ضحك)
CA: Twitter's going crazy. Twitter's going mad.
كريس: التويتر سيصبح مجنونا ومهوسا.
So that stock market experiment.
تلك التجربة عن سوق الأسهم
This could be the first experiment that secures its funding forevermore,
يمكن أن تكون التجربة الأولى التي تؤمّن تمويل أبدي
right, if successful?
إذا نجحت، صحيح؟
DE: Well, that's right, I wouldn't have to write to NIH anymore.
ديفيد: هذا صحيح، لن أحتاج لمعاهد الصحة الوطنية الأمريكية بعد الآن
CA: Well look, just to be skeptical for a minute,
كريس: حسنًا ، دعني أكون محايدا
I mean, this is amazing, but isn't most of the evidence so far
نعم هذا مدهش، لكن أليست معظم الشواهد حتى الآن
that sensory substitution works,
تؤكد أن نجاح البدائل الحسية،
not necessarily that sensory addition works?
ليس بالضرورة أن يعني نجاح الإضافات الحسية؟
I mean, isn't it possible that the blind person can see through their tongue
أعني، أليس من الممكن أن يرى الأعمي عبر لسانه
because the visual cortex is still there, ready to process,
لأن القشرة البصرية للدماغ موجودة فيه
and that that is needed as part of it?
وهذا مطلوب كجزء من العملية؟
DE: That's a great question. We actually have no idea
ديفيد: هذا سؤال جميل، في الحقيقة ليست لدينا فكرة
what the theoretical limits are of what kind of data the brain can take in.
عن الحدود النظرية لنوع المعلومات التي يمكن أن يتقبلها الدماغ
The general story, though, is that it's extraordinarily flexible.
لكن عموما، الدماغ مرِن بصورة غريبة
So when a person goes blind, what we used to call their visual cortex
فعندما يصبح الشخص أعمى، ما نستخدمه للاتصال بالقشرة البصرية
gets taken over by other things, by touch, by hearing, by vocabulary.
يمكن أن يكون اللمس أو السمع أو المفردات.
So what that tells us is that the cortex is kind of a one-trick pony.
ما يعنيه هذا أن القشرة البصرية نوع من المترجمات.
It just runs certain kinds of computations on things.
تطبق نوع معين من العمليات الحسابية على الأشياء
And when we look around at things like braille, for example,
إذا أخذنا طريقة بريل، على سبيل المثال
people are getting information through bumps on their fingers.
فإن الناس يحصلون على المعلومات عبر أناملهم
So I don't think we have any reason to think there's a theoretical limit
لذلك أعتقد أنه لا يوجد حدود نظرية
that we know the edge of.
نحن نعلم نهايتها.
CA: If this checks out, you're going to be deluged.
كريس: إذا تحقق هذا، ستُصبح مشغولا جدا.
There are so many possible applications for this.
فهناك العديد من التطبيقات ستكون بإنتظارك
Are you ready for this? What are you most excited about, the direction it might go?
هل أنت جاهز لهذا؟ ولأي تطبيق متحمسٌ أكثر؟
DE: I mean, I think there's a lot of applications here.
ديفيد: نعم هناك الكثير من التطبيقات
In terms of beyond sensory substitution, the things I started mentioning
من ناحية البدائل الحسية، لكن ما بدأت أذكره
about astronauts on the space station, they spend a lot of their time
عن رواد الفضاء في المحطة الفضائية، إنهم يبذلون الكثير من وقتهم
monitoring things, and they could instead just get what's going on,
في مراقبة الأشياء، فباستطاعتهم معرفة كل مايجري فقط في لحظة،
because what this is really good for is multidimensional data.
لأن هذا فعلاً مناسب بالنسبة للبيانات متعددة الأبعاد.
The key is this: Our visual systems are good at detecting blobs and edges,
يعتبر نظامنا البصري جيّد في التقاط النقط والحواف،
but they're really bad at what our world has become,
لكنه سيء جدًا مقارنة بما أصبح عليه عالمنا
which is screens with lots and lots of data.
حيث الشاشات المليئة بالكثير من البيانات
We have to crawl that with our attentional systems.
تحتاج للكثير من التركيز والانتباه.
So this is a way of just feeling the state of something,
لذلك بهذه الطريقة فقط نستطيع إدراك حالة الشيء،
just like the way you know the state of your body as you're standing around.
بنفس الطريقة التي تعرف بها موضع جسدك وأنت تقف في مكان ما.
So I think heavy machinery, safety, feeling the state of a factory,
مثلا الآليات الثقيلة والأمن تعي بحالة المصنع
of your equipment, that's one place it'll go right away.
وبحالة معداتك، في هذا المسار سيكون نجاحه المشروع.
CA: David Eagleman, that was one mind-blowing talk. Thank you very much.
ديفيد إيغلمان، لقد كانت هذه من المحادثات التي تعصف بالذهن، شكرا جزيلًا.
DE: Thank you, Chris. (Applause)
ديفيد: شكرًا كريس. (تصفيق)